{"tossups": [{"question": "Nearly 2,000 people died when the<em> Sultana</em> exploded in this river, but John Wilkes Booth died the day before, so the tragedy received shockingly little press coverage. Monks Mound was built on the eastern banks of this river, which names a civilization that built the city of Cahokia. A control structure was built to reduce its flow into the Atchafalaya River. For ten points, name this American river whose source was identified in 1832 as Minnesota\u2019s Lake Itasca, from which it flows to the Gulf of Mexico.", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The success of this work led to a plagiarization lawsuit from Harold Courlander. Sequels to this work include \u201cThe Gift\u201d and \u201cThe Next Generations.\u201d Tom Moore teaches the intricacies of cockfighting in this series, in which Jemmy deserts the Confederate Army. It ends with Chicken George tracing his lineage from Africa to Tennessee. ABC aired this series, an adaptation of a \u201cSaga of an American Family,\u201d in 1977. For ten points, name this novel and TV miniseries about Kunta Kinte, inspired by the ancestors of author Alex Haley.", "answer": "<b> Roots</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "In this country, a moral pressure known as \u201cwindow guidance\u201d prevented banks from making major lending pushes. A company based in this country introduced the \u201cjust in time\u201d system to improve efficiency. This country\u2019s prime minister suggested a \u201cThree Arrows\u201d approach to address its low inflation rate, decreasing productivity, and aging working population. \u201cAbenomics\u201d [ah-bay-nomics] was undertaken in, for ten points, what country that experienced the \u201cLost Decade\u201d after poor economic performance from companies such as Toyota and Sony?", "answer": "<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "A video taken at this event shows a Mi-8 helicopter colliding with a cable suspended from a crane, causing the helicopter to crash. The TORCH Report predicted tens of thousands of deaths due to the effects of this event. This was the first event to be classified as a INES level 7. The<em> samosely</em> illegally live in the \u201czone of alienation\u201d near the site of this event; that exclusion zone includes the Red Forest and the city of Pripyat, which became a ghost town in this event\u2019s aftermath. For ten points, name this 1986 meltdown of a Ukrainian nuclear power plant.", "answer": "<b> Chernobyl</b> disaster (accept additional information and synonyms of disaster)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "While serving as this President\u2019s Secretary of War, George Crawford was implicated in the Galphin Affair. This President\u2019s Secretary of State negotiated an effort to build the Nicaragua Canal in the Clayton-Bulwer Treaty. Before becoming president, this man defeated Santa Anna at the Battle of Buena Vista during the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this President, nicknamed \u201cOld Rough and Ready,\u201d whose death after a year in office promoted Millard Fillmore to the presidency.", "answer": "Zachary<b> Taylor</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Karl Goetz created a series of medals that depict this event with captions like \u201cBusiness Above All\u201d and \u201cNo Contraband.\u201d The \u201ccoal dust\u201d theory probably does not explain the second explosion that occurred during this event. This event may have been avoided had the zig-zag maneuver been carried out, and it was predicted by a newspaper which acknowledged a state of war between two nations. For ten points, name this event in which a British passenger ship was torpedoed by a German U-Boat, prompting the U.S. to enter World War I.", "answer": "<b> sinking of the</b> RMS<b> Lusitania</b> (accept equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This group was established with the Oath of Pontida. This group utilized the<em> carroccio</em>, which was defended by a group of knights known as the Company of Death. One emperor claimed power over members of this group at the Diet of Roncaglia, but that emperor, Frederick Barbarossa, was decisively defeated by this group at the Battle of Legnano. This group was rended obsolete after the end of the Hohenstaufen dynasty. For ten points, name this medieval alliance of Northern Italian city-states which opposed the influence of the Holy Roman Empire.", "answer": "<b> Lombard League</b> (accept<b> Lega Lombarda</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A ruler of this dynasty used \u201cHanging Judge\u201d George Jeffreys to punish participants of a rebellion against him in the Bloody Assizes. A war with the Dutch during this dynasty\u2019s reign included the devastating Raid on the Medway. An interregnum during this dynasty was dominated by elites known as the Grandees and included a government called the Protectorate. William and Mary\u2019s Glorious Revolution overthrew a ruler from, for ten points, what dynasty that succeeded the Tudor Dynasty when James I ascended to the English throne?", "answer": "House of<b> Stuart</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Pedro Almodovar\u2019s Glen Valley was announced as part of this event. As part of this event, the ownership of Wintris [vin-tris] by Sigmundur David was revealed during an interview with David, shortly before he stepped aside as Prime Minister. Mossack Fonseca was blamed for this event, whose source began in 2015 but became broadly public in April 2016 as the existence of 2.6 terabytes of data, involving over 10 million documents, was announced. For ten points, name this event in which the existence of hundreds of thousands of offshore companies was unintentionally revealed by a Central American firm.", "answer": "the leak of the<b> Panama Papers</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "In this work\u2019s epilogue, a trio of ghosts including Queen Tye sing wordlessly. An offstage rendition of Psalm 104 follows a hymn in this opera that is to be sung in the audience\u2019s native language. This opera is the final part of its composer\u2019s Portrait trilogy. Its libretto, which is mostly taken from records of the Amarna period, depicts a king who sings the \u201cHymn to the Sun\u201d and marries Nefertiti. For ten points, name this Philip Glass opera about a monotheistic pharaoh.", "answer": "<b> Akhnaten</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {}, {"question": "This author described a \u201csense of dissatisfaction\u201d and the silent question \u201cIs this all?\u201d in the opening to one work. This co-founder of NARAL and author of<em> The Second Stage</em> described \u201cthe problem that has no name\u201d as an inner voice saying \u201cI want something more than my husband and my children and my home\u201d in her most famous work. The National Organization for Women was first led by, for ten points, what American thinker, the author of<em> The Feminine Mystique</em>?", "answer": "Betty<b> Friedan</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this phenomenon in which electrons are emitted when light is shined upon metal.", "answer": "<b> photoelectric</b> effect", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The initial invasion of this war may have sought to capture Jaber al-Sabah from Dasman Palace, but he fled and ruled in exile from a Saudi Arabian hotel room. In this war, the (+) </b> <b>Republican Guard was defeated in a vast desert at the Battle of 73 Easting, called \u201cthe last great tank battle of the (*) </b> 20th century.\u201d Coalition forces in this war were led by \u201cStormin\u2019\u201dNorman Schwarzkopf, who devised this war\u2019s tactical plan, Operation Desert Storm. For ten points, name this 1991 war in which the U.S. responded to Iraq\u2019s invasion of Kuwait.", "answer": "Persian<b> Gulf</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man was known as the \u201cadolescent butcher\u201d and gained an epithet after defeating Hiarbas. He married Aemilia Scaura after aiding her father against Gnaeus Papirius Carbo.</b> <b>This general forced the surrender of Tigranes the Great in a war against (+)</b> <b>Mithridates</b> <b>VI. He helped Metellus Pius suppress Sertorius, and the</b><em><b> Lex Gabinia</b></em><b> gave him maritime powers to quash the Cilician pirates. After losing to a former ally at (*)</b> Pharsalus, he fled to Egypt, where Ptolemy XII ordered him dead. For ten points, name this member of the First Triumvirate with Crassus and Caesar.", "answer": "<b> Pompey</b> the Great (or Gnaeus<b> Pompeius Magnus</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man rose to his highest post after leading the ships</b><em><b> Novara</b></em><b>,</b><em><b> Saida</b></em><b>, and</b><em><b> Helgoland </b></em><b>in a raid on the Otranto Barrage. Following his overthrow, this man\u2019s capital was taken in a one hundred day siege. This man first allied with the Axis over anger at the Treaty of (+) Trianon, though his son was later kidnapped and wrapped into a carpet during Operation Panzerfaust, which was planned by Otto Skorzeny. (*)</b> Ferenc Szalai [fer-entz SA-lie] of the Arrow Cross Party took power after the overthrow of, for ten points, what admiral who led Hungary in World War II?", "answer": "Miklos<b> Horthy</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In response to being called an Uncle Tom for her role in this film, one actress said \u201cI\u2019d rather make 700 dollars a week playing a maid, than seven dollars being one.\u201d This film\u2019s premiere was hosted by Mayor William Hartsfield, though local laws prevented (+) Hattie McDaniel, who became the first African-American Oscar winner for her role in this film, from attending. Melanie Hamilton was played by Olivia de Havilland, one of the few (*) </b>surviving cast members from this film. The inflation-adjusted highest grossing film of all time is, for ten points, what 1939 film starring Vivien Leigh and Clark Gable as Scarlett O\u2019Hara and Rhett Butler, which was based on a Margaret Mitchell novel?", "answer": "<b> Gone With the Wind</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s overtures for peace talks were recorded in \u201cThe Vital Letters of [this man], Khrushchev, and Dulles.\u201d He noted that colonization was justified with proper use of land in his \u201cEthics of War.\u201d A manifesto named for this man and (+) Albert Einstein became the founding charter of the Pugwash Conferences. His work \u201cOn Denoting\u201d discusses definite and indefinite descriptions, and this author of (*)</b> \u201cWhy I Am Not a Christian\u201d was an outspoken proponent of nuclear disarmament. For ten points, name this British philosopher who collaborated with Alfred, Lord Whitehead in<em> Principia Mathematica</em>.", "answer": "Bertrand<b> Russell</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>Judge John Sirica tried to make legal progress in this scandal by sentencing Howard Hunt to 40 years in prison. This event was investigated by the Ervin Committee. Egil Krogh and (+) Gordon Liddy were among the \u201cPlumbers\u201d who were arrested in this event and who were tied via a slush fund to a Committee to Re-Elect the (*)</b> President. Bob Woodward and Carl Bernstein\u2019s investigation of this event was aided by Deep Throat. For ten points, name this scandal that began with a break-in at a Washington, D.C. hotel that eventually led to Richard Nixon\u2019s resignation.", "answer": "<b> Watergate</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}